New Haven Railroad Construction Photograph Collection
© 2005 University of Connecticut
New Haven Railroad Construction Photograph Collection.
circa 1890s.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
New Haven Railroad.
.25 linear feet (19 photographs).
MSS20020023
The New Haven Railroad was formed in 1872 through the merger of the Hartford and New Haven Railroad and the New York and New Haven Railroad. On January 1, 1969, it formally folded into the PennCentral Railroad system.
History
For almost one hundred years the New York, New Haven, and Hartford Railroad, better known as the New Haven Railroad, was the primary means of passenger and freight transportation in southern New England. Chartered in 1872, this merger between the New York & New Haven and Hartford & New Haven railroads later included the long desired rail link between Boston and New York. Approximately one hundred small independent railroads were built in southern New England between 1826 and the 1880s. By 1904, the majority were absorbed into the vast New Haven system. At its peak in 1929, the New Haven Railroad owned and operated 2,131 miles of track throughout eastern New York, Connecticut, Massachusetts, and Rhode Island.
The local railroad lines that eventually became part of the New Haven system developed in response to local business and transportation needs. Unlike the Western states, where railroads preceded and shaped settlement, in the Northeast they served primarily to link existing towns, businesses, and markets. The New Haven system thus developed as a result of numerous consolidations and mergers. The New Haven traced its founding to 1826, when one of its predecessor companies originated, but the New York, New Haven and Hartford Railroad was not chartered until 1872. The company followed the pattern of consolidation established by the Pennsylvania Railroad and other companies, particularly after 1889, when major lines in Connecticut, Rhode Island, and southern Massachusetts provided a strong network linking New York and Boston. By 1890, company revenue exceeded $100,000,000 per year, and the New Haven employed 4,000 people to serve twelve million passengers annually.
This success led a wealthy group of New York investors, headed by J. P. Morgan, to seek and gain control of the New Haven's board. In 1903, Morgan installed Charles Mellen as president of the railroad. Together Morgan and Mellen set out to achieve a complete monopoly of transportation in New England. Substantial improvements to the system were made during the Mellen years, including electrification of rail lines between Woodlawn, New York, and New Haven, Connecticut, and construction of a power generating plant in Cos Cob, Connecticut. These accomplishments, however, were overshadowed by Morgan's ambitious schemes to dominate all modes of transportation in New England. Steamboat lines, trolley companies, and other railroad lines were purchased regardless of price and incorporated into the New Haven system.
An investigation of the New Haven's activities by Louis Brandeis in 1907 revealed the overextended railroad was on the verge of financial collapse. Morgan's death in 1913 and Mellen's subsequent resignation brought to a close a stormy period in the New Haven's history.
During the First World War, all of the railroads in the United States, including the New Haven Railroad, were operated by the federal government. After the war, under Edward Pearson, President through 1928, the railroad was able to recover partially, despite increasing competition from automobiles, by sharing in the national economic growth of the 1920s. The company tried to meet this transportation competition by forming the New England Transportation Company, which operated a fleet of trucks and buses. Recovery of the New Haven, however, was cut short by the Depression of the 1930s, and in 1935 the New Haven plunged into bankruptcy. The company remained in trusteeship until 1947, when it returned to private ownership.
A series of struggles for control of the company in the post World War II period severely weakened the management of the company and its ability to adapt to changes in the transportation industry. The completion of the Connecticut Turnpike and other superhighways and the start of air shuttle service between Boston and New York intensified competition. The company's historic liability as a railroad overburdened with many short, costly branch lines further accelerated its decline.
On 7 July 1961, the New Haven Railroad once again went into receivership. A seven year trusteeship period followed, culminating in the absorption of the New Haven in the Penn Central system on 1 January 1969. Three years later the Penn Central itself collapsed into bankruptcy. The former components of the New Haven Railroad were divided among several entities. Freight service was assumed by Conrail when it was formed in 1976, although the Providence & Worcester also provided freight service on portions of the former New Haven, as did a few other operators. Passenger commuter service was funded by the New York Metropolitan Transit Authority and the Connecticut Department of Transportation. Long-haul passenger service was provided by Amtrak beginning in 1971. After 1976 passenger commuter service was operated by Conrail. In 1982, the United States Congress passed legislation that forced Conrail to divest itself of its commuter rail lines. On 1 January 1983, Metro-North Commuter Railroad, under joint ownership of the states of New York and Connecticut, took over all commuter passenger service. Amtrak continued to handle all long-haul passenger service.
The history of the New Haven Railroad reveals a company formed by one of the classic merger and consolidation patterns of the late 19th century, which was later unable to respond effectively to major changes in the transportation industry. The company's rapid growth, collapse, temporary recovery, and final dissolution offer a dramatic story, with government regulation, internal management decisions, and market competition playing important roles in the company's history.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of 19 photographs of the construction of New Haven Railroad tracks and bridges in the Norwalk and East Norwalk area in Connecticut, from the 1890s.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of New England railroad records. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Organizations:
New York, New Haven and Hartford Railroad Company.
Subjects:
Railroads--New England--Photographs.; Railroad construction workers--Photographs.; Railroads--Design and construction.
Document Types:
Photographs.
Occupations:
Railroad corporation.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Photographs were donated by Peter E. Lynch of Old Saybrook, Connecticut, in May 2002 and August 2003.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series I: Collection, ca. 1890s
  - Bridge with houses and trees, ca. 1890s (Other 2002-0023.ph1)
    4.25×5.25 inches, B&W. Sepia toned mounted photograph of bridge (possibly railroad bridge) and dirt road passing under bridge. Houses on left of bridge and behind bridge. Possible station to right of bridge. Stonewall in front of house on left.
  - Housatonic Railroad train tunnel, ca. 1890s (Other 2002-0023.ph2)
    4.25×5.25 inches, B&W. Sepia toned mounted photograph of railroad tracks emerging from darkened tunnel. Jagged rock surrounding tunnel. Trees and shrubs on surface above tunnel.
  - Railroad bridge crossing river, ca. 1890s (Other 2002-0023.ph3)
    4.25×5.25 inches, B&W. Sepia toned mounted photograph of a railroad bridge crossing a river with a small rowboat resting on the shore. Grassy hill with electrical pole to the right beneath the bridge. Trees and electrical poles to the left of bridge.
  - Railroad bridge crossing land, ca. 1890s (Other 2002-0023.ph4)
    4.25×5.25 inches, B&W. Sepia toned mounted photograph of railroad bridge crossing expanse of land and possibly body of water. Tree in left foreground. Electrical poles next to bridge. Fence lines possible waterway to the right.
  - Link and pin couplers on railroad track, ca. 1890s (Other 2002-0023.ph5)
    4.25×5.25 inches, B&W. Sepia toned mounted photograph of link and pin couplers on splitting railroad track. Railroad sign, trees, and houses to left. Electrical poles and railroad ties on right. Rails leading to possible station to far right.
  - East Norwalk Depot, ca. 1890s (Other 2002-0023.ph6)
    4.25×5.25 inches, B&W. Sepia toned mounted photograph of East Norwalk depot. Two tracks on foreground with electrical poles following along tracks. Houses to left behind depot and track. Tree next to depot on right.
  - Railroad track under construction in ditch, ca. 1890s (Other 2002-0023.ph7)
    4.25×5.25 inches, B&W. Sepia toned mounted photograph of possibly unfinished railroad track in rocky ditch. Workmen, electrical poles above ditch to left. Possible construction materials in ditch background. Duplicate photo in collection.
  - Building road bridge, ca. 1890s (Other 2002-0023.ph8)
    4.25×5.25 inches, B&W. Sepia toned mounted photograph of construction of road bridge. In ditch beneath bridge in foreground are rocks, construction equipment, workmen. In ditch in background are horses and workmen. Duplicate photo in collection.
  - Railroad track construction, ca. 1890s (Other 2002-0023.ph9)
    4.25×5.25 inches, B&W. Sepia toned mounted photograph of railroad track under construction. Workers along track to left. Carts filled with dirt, workers to right of track. Buildings, equipment, above ditch to right. Duplicate photo in collection.
  - Railroad track construction, ca. 1890s (Other 2002-0023.ph10)
    4.25×5.25 inches, B&W. Sepia toned mounted photograph. Cardboard cracked along entire width of photo. Railroad track construction with workmen, carts and equipment to right of tracks. Bridge crosses over tracks. Duplicate photo in collection.
  - Railroad track construction, ca. 1890s (Other 2002-0023.ph11)
    4.25×5.25 inches, B&W. Sepia toned mounted photograph of men and work supplies on railroad tracks. Workers with horses, carts filled with dirt are between the tracks and high wall of ditch. Workers on hill above railroad tracks.
  - Railroad track construction, ca. 1890s (Other 2002-0023.ph12)
    4.25×5.25 inches, B&W. Sepia toned mounted photograph of construction on railroad track. Men stand on tracks on right. Bridge crosses right track in background. Men, horses on lower level to left work on separate track.
  - Construction along railroad track, ca. 1890s (Other 2002-0023.ph13)
    4.25×5.25 inches, B&W. Sepia toned mounted photograph of group of men clearing away earth on hill. Horses, men, and carts filled with earth stand below between wall and railroad track.
  - Building Road Bridge, East Norwalk, ca. 1890s (Other 2002-0023.ph14)
    4.25×5.25 inches, B&W. Sepia toned mounted photograph of construction on railroad track. Men and horses with wagons throughout photographs. Depicts construction of stone bridge next to railroad tracks.
  - New Haven Station at South Norwalk, Connecticut, ca. 1890-1891 (Other 2002-0023.ph15)
    4.25×5.25 inches, B&W. Sepia toned mounted photograph of railroad station. Freight car visible next to station. Tracks in foreground. Telephone or telegraph wires in background.